K Gangadhar - Sr. Data Engineer

15338 NE 9th Place Bellevue, WA-98007 | gangk@amazon.com +1 425 591 2121 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/gangk

Objective:

Highly motivated, results-driven Software Engineer with experience in full data & database management technologies. A self-quick learner who is willing to embrace new challenges and is able to learn and use new programs with ease; Flexible team player who also works well independently.

Technical Skills:

- Relational Databases: Oracle 7.x to 11gR2(DG with FSF), MySQL 5.x, & PostgreSQL 9.x.
- No-SQL databases: Cassandra, Hbase, Mongo-db and DynamoDB etc.
- Big Data: Redshift/Hadoop/Spark etc.
- Knowledge of Machine learning tools/frameworks.
- AWS Cloud: RDS/Aurora, DMS, EMR, EBS, S3, EC2, Glue etc.
- Operating Systems: RHEL, HP-UX, Sun Solaris & AIX
- Languages: Shell, Python & Scala
- Basic Linux/UNIX Administration & Knowledge of distributed storage & database paradigms

Career Interests:

- Design, Build and Maintain scalable data & database infrastructure for rapidly growing services
- Data model & Architect data engineering platform for advanced analytics/machine learning

Professional Experience:

Amazon.com Inc. Seattle, US (Feb 2011 – till date):

Sr. Data Engineer in teams of International Retail, Fulfillment & Transportation, within Amazon.com Services; part of team with size 10-15 members which is responsible for designing & managing all kinds of persistence solutions such as Redshift, RDS/Aurora (MySQL & Postgres) & DynamoDB etc. including Big data and reporting systems on AWS infrastructure.

- Dealing with end-to-end DB operations/activities such as schema design & implementation.
- Data model, schema design & develop against various database systems.
- Query optimization, instance tuning and benchmarking database performance.
- Planning & performing on data/database migration from one engine to another DB engine.
- Participate in design reviews and evaluate right persistence solutions for services.
- Plan and migrate data from one relational engine to another.
- Help the customer teams to configure/deploy ETL jobs and troubleshoot if any issues.
- Collaborate with Data Scientists to implement advanced analytics algorithms that exploit our rich data sets for statistical analysis, prediction, clustering, and machine learning.

- Collaborate with Business Intelligence Engineers to recognize and help adopt best practices in reporting and analysis: data integrity, test design, analysis, validation, and documentation.
- Interface with other technology teams to extract, transform, and load data from a wide variety of data sources using SQL and AWS big data technologies.
- Perform data migration/loads and configure & schedule ETL jobs
- Automate regular/redundant database tasks using shell/python
- DB scaling work, capacity planning & DB operational issues etc.
- Provision & Plan hardware for DB infrastructure and work closely with HW engineering.
- Securing Databases/Schemas as per company info-sec guidelines.
- Work with application teams closely and help migrate the services/data to AWS resources.
- Continuous follow up on outstanding issues and drive them to resolution.
- Deep dive the issues for root cause and plan on permanent fix.

CGI India Pvt Ltd, Bangalore, India (Sep, 2007 – Feb, 2011):

Senior Software Engineer (DBA) and part of CSB engagement with team size 6 members, which was responsible for supporting & managing all Bell Canada & its subsidiary company database systems (150+ Oracle & MySQL) in 24X7 support model; primarily responsible for database production support i.e. dealing with all kinds of database issues and working towards quick & permanent resolutions.

- Install and build databases/schemas & upgrade databases as per business requirements.
- Automate regular database tasks & configure/deploy monitoring.
- Perform database/schema changes as per company change policies.
- Optimize database jobs, stored procedures and long running queries.
- Help dev teams to deal with/write complex queries and provide guidance on data quality.
- Build DR procedures for production databases and have tested & verified recovery procedures
- Troubleshoot all DB issues, root cause and implement permanent fix.
- Communicate with client on regular basis to understand to their continuous data needs.

Education & Credits:

Bachelor of Technology – Graduate (2003-2007)

Kakatiya University – State Govt. University, Warangal, Telangana, India Major in Computer Science and Engineering

Personal Details:

Legal Name: Gangadhararao Katikireddy

Date of Birth: 07/04/1985

Nationality: INDIA

Immigration and work authorization: H1-B with Labor & I-140 approved